We're gonna get right to it. You know when it
comes to knowing the value of vintage treasures
Our first guest is an expert here to share his
always helpful tips. We welcome back antique
appraiser Gary Germer Gary
Great to see you. Thanks. Thanks for
having me over. Oh this first of all,
we cannot stop talking
about this set of silver
It's incredible. We don't know exactly what it
is. Well, will you tell me how did this come
to your into your clutches?
Well, we work a lot in our business
I do with the appraisal business
help people with donations
So I had a client call me
up and he said he had this
Set of silver silver plated stuff from his
grandfather and he's thinking of donating it
But what kind of one know what it was
worth before so he could pick a deduction
Sure, and I said we'll send me some pictures
of it and and the markings and all that
And so he did and I nearly
fell over no kidding
And Wow on the base of it where the markings
are, you know, let me bang it together
It has a Tiffany mark
and if I have that stream
It says Sterling and that's where my appraisal
skills come in that I could tell him it was Sterling
yeah, cuz it says right on there and
Okay, and then the marks
from Tiffany and Company
There if you can date you can kind of date it
from when this was done it has an M on there
He thought that meant it was like a secondary
thing and it's not it was for the director a guy
named John Morse
Was the director in when this was made this
dates to 1867 director at Tiffany yeah?
He was directing what happened Tiffany
started out in 1830 s as a high end
Stationery business oh okay an office step and
then they added more luxury goods and they worked
with this Morris and his
sons to get silver
And then they merged their company in Tiffany
bought him out and Morris was then the director
so you can date it about
about 1867. Incredible. The other thing about it
that so so when they asked me what did I think?
Yeah. I said well from the photos a quick 20 to
25,000 and of course there was silence at the
other end of the line. Yeah yeah yeah. And then
he says well I got to talk to my wife so I didn't
know what that meant. Smart man. Yeah and so
then he come back we decided to go ahead and sell
it
can you sell it for us and I said I
think so I want to research it more.
So researching it more
1867 was the year of the French World's Fair
and it was the first time Americans were taken
seriously as an American style and Tiffany led
the charge. They had a huge display of silver
and art
that was an all-American design. Wow. And it was
that set us up and Tiffany led the charge and
so
I've contacted Tiffany to see if they in their
archives has any history of this because they
all have serial numbers on them.
Right. And was it used in the Expo?
Yeah. So that will add to the value. Yeah.
Researching it currently I've almost doubled the
value 40 to 50,000
is about where we're at and if we can say that
it was in Paris at one point and he got it in
Paris
it could almost double it again. Oh my gosh. So
wait would Tiffany ever want to buy back something
like this? That was the first thing they asked
me would they be willing to sell it back to us
and I
said well let's find out. If the price is right.
Yeah exactly. So what would you use this for?
It's called an Epern.
And it was it was meant for your dining table or
the side buffet. I think it was mainly honestly
a
sculptural work of art. But it could be used
to serve things with. You have these dishes and
you
turn it a quarter turn and they come off.
So you could bring things out and set it in.
It hasn't
been used much because if you look inside it
has a gold wash. Yeah. And that can get polished
off.
Okay. And so I figured out. I figured
out what we can use it for Gary. Yeah.
You'll just sell it to
for 20 bucks I'm figuring that the
chips go up here yeah okay and all the
different dips go in here exactly they that's
better than the little wieners over here
the deviled eggs in there we're all set
it is that's better I told my friend
that although the guy said he said what
it was before I said let's just separate
your colors of M&Ms there you go I love it
oh my gosh that is absolutely incredible so
there's a nice thing to find in the back
of your closet no kidding no kidding
yeah now you have some pieces of jewelry
got some jewels here I better not move
the camera man gets mad at me when I touch
things the photographers do yes I hear about you
afterwards yeah a different client his
mother had passed and he brought in his
mother's jewelry his attorney had referred him
to us to sell his mother's jewelry and he was
just going to leave it and have me inventory
and call him later and I said no no no let's
get this out and look at it there's a of the
collect of all that these were the some of the
best pieces of all the jewelry there were a
lot of jewelry that was in there and I said
there was probably 50 60 pieces of jewelry
and I said we need to photograph it because
you got to be really careful you know because
you can trust my integrity you don't always
trust my memory right you know I want to make
sure I know whose is what yeah oh I think
the same way okay this piece here the necklace
is a choker dates to about 1905 the the clasp
is platinum with European cut diamonds wow
and it's really the class goes in front in
this case exactly
yeah it's a choker and the clasp would be
the piece of jewelry there and it's big it's
it's a real period piece it would be you think
of the Edwardian yeah the Titanic I whenever
I sell something from this period I'll put
a sign that says you know from the Titanic
and then in small print era that makes sense
and then this three and a third carat square
cut diamond was in there it's a solitaire
diamond and what other than being it's a really
nice piece yeah
yeah I wanted to mention is that what we're
seeing a lot of in the diamond business especially
anything a carat and larger they make lab made
ones they hit they sell them under different
trade names right and they talked about it's
a real diamond it's chemically a real diamond
the little needle tester thing we used to
test shows it as being a real diamond it's
a diamond however and they've been making
them since 1957 but it's been in the last
10 years that they've seen them more and more
yeah the problem is is that they don't and
sitting well why would I pay.
because in the last 10 years in the last 10
years in the last 10 years in the last 10 years
in the last 10 years in the last 10 years
in the last 10 years in the last 10 years in
the last 10 years in the last 10 years in
the last 10 years in the last 10 years in the
10 years in the last 10 years in the last
10 years in the last 10 years in the last 10
years in the last 10 years in the last 10 years
in the last 10 years in the last 10 years in
the last 10 years in the last 10 years in the
last 10 years in the last 10 years in the last
Institute of America there in Los
Angeles they are the standard bearers
you send it to them and for a couple
hundred dollars they'll give a complete
analysis of your stone and then they'll
along the girdle along the very edge of
it with a laser they put in a serial
number oh okay what brand you're that
you can't see it you can't see it unless
it's under a microscope you see it so it
doesn't affect the diamond but it's
really and so how much did you say this
diamond is worth that you found out
that's about 25,000 Wow in this necklace
about 5,000 I think you probably get
this question a lot how can you tell
real pearls from non real pearls well if
you can there's a couple of things you I
look at them first with a loop and
you're looking for a little bit of
inconsistency to them when you also the
thing if you're going to be buying it
you put it on a piece of white white
paper can be just from your computer
paper whatever something white and then
you can see the color variations and how
well it looks and then you can see the
color variations and how well it looks
match they are if you go to sell it you
put on something black because it even
makes anything look wonderful sure so
that's the other way they have a slight
roughness to them where a synthetic
pearl or the costume but will be
completely smooth and so that's another
way okay gotcha now this piece of art
here tell me about this well the lady
who brought this to me and there's a
second one she has two of them she
bought them at a state and a state sale
because she liked them and she liked
Barnes and she was from the Northeast
okay and it reminded me of the
because she liked Barnes and
she was from the Northeast
of the you know snowfall the northeast
and soft pain and I thought oh that's a
nice painting I like it you know and
I could live with that that's really
pretty and then she says is it right
about the artist and so we did some
research she'd had it on her wall for
over 10 years and filifrenzid you know I
think that's a better painting than you
thought so this artist name it's kind of
worth forty to fifty thousand dollars
each you know stop yeah so really she
wouldn't tell me what she paid for him
but I did ask her well so are you gonna
make a profit on him when I sell him for
you she goes oh I'll do fine yeah and
the fact that she she liked it said
something about the art that that's not
my thing no but you know no I thought
it's me either but I as far as I think
it's beautiful I think it's fun and
but again I yeah if I saw this is where
people think an appraiser will know
everything off the top their head so if
I'd walked into an estate sale I'd
say oh that's nice and if they had two
thousand dollars on it I'd say no yeah
you know yeah and walk away I wouldn't
necessarily research it right so I can
usually tell you if something's really
bad but you don't necessarily know how
something good it is and we have time to
research absolutely oh my gosh all
good tips Gary thank you so much that's
fascinating hundred thousand dollars I
brought it in today all right we'll be
right back with more
am Northwest but first
you